Alice Owens Caufield papers, Inclusive: 1947-1992, Bulk:1980-1986
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Alice Owens Caufield papers
Inclusive: 1947-1992, Bulk:1980-1986
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3567
Caufield, Alice Owens
1 box
The Alice Owens Caufield papers contain the personal papers of Caufield, including speeches, research, and programs from church and civic events primarily held in Waco, Texas.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Biography/Profile
Alice Owens Caufield (1907-1999) was born on 1907 November 5 at a farm near the present day traffic circle in Waco, Texas. At the age of five, her mother died, and she learned to handle all operations of a farm with her father, sister, and grandparents. When her grandparents died, she became the primary person carrying out all household farm chores. In 1929, she married James Caufield (1896-1970); Alice and James each had a son from a previous marriage at the time of their marriage to each other. She graduated from A.J. Moore High School in 1927, then attended college at Paul Quinn College, Texas Southern University, and Baylor University, obtaining degrees in history and sociology, and training in education. Beginning her career as a teacher's aide, she also served as a nurse's aide, secretary, legal aid, outreach/social worker, and eventually program director of the organization at that time known as the Young Women's Christian Association, or YWCA. Specifically, she worked for many years with the Blue Triangle YWCA in Waco, a branch of a Houston organization that sought to host safe meeting and educational spaces and events for women and girls of color. Her longtime affiliation with the group began the year after they were founded, as she joined in 1938. Alice Owens Caufield passed away on 1999 March 14 and is buried in Robinson Cemetery, McLennan County, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Alice Owens Caufield papers contain a variety of programs from African American churches in Waco and Amarillo, programs from memorial services held in Waco, and programs from Waco civic organizations and events. Notable among these are two specific programs: one from the dedication of a Doris Miller memorial in Waco in 1984, and a service in honor of Martin Luther King Jr. in 1986, sponsored by the Waco Ministerial Alliance. Other materials in the collection include speeches given by Caufield and research materials used to write the speeches. Having grown up hearing stories about the lynching of Jesse Washington, Caufield made sure that the importance of preserving African American history was imparted to the next generation, as many of her speeches were to groups of girls about Black history.
Arrangement
The Alice Owens Caufield papers were arranged in folders with titles prior to the current round of processing. The previous folder titles were retained. Currently, the collection is arranged in one series: I. Personal.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3567. Acquired 2003-10-15
Related Resources
Related references
Crabtree, Mari N. "The Devil is Watching You: Lynching and Southern Memory, 1940-1970." PhD dissertation, Cornell University, 2014. Accessed 2020 September 2.
Find A Grave, Inc. "Alice O. Caufield." Memorial #30946373. Databases. Accessed 2020 September 2.
"Home Nursing Class Rites Set Monday." Waco Tribune-Herald, 1958 December 28. Accessed 2020 September 2.
"The Blue Triangle: History." Blue Triangle Community Center. Accessed 2020 September 2.
Warren, Mary. "Retirement Reception Scheduled for Y's Alice Caufield Today." Waco News Tribune, 1973 July 23.
Index Terms
Subjects
African American Baptists -- Texas -- Waco.; African American churches -- Texas -- Waco.; African American women -- Texas -- History.; African Americans -- Texas -- Waco -- Biography; City churches -- Texas -- Waco.; Women -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Programs (Publications).; Speeches.
- Personal, 1947-1992; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains a variety of materials from the life of Alice Owens Caufield, including various civic organizations, churches, speeches she gave to groups, memorial service programs, and information on local and national African American history. This series is in excellent condition.
  - Biographical, 1947-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Speeches (1 of 2), 1957-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Speeches (2 of 2), 1957-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Second Missionary Baptist Church, Waco, Texas, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mt. Zion Baptist Church, Amarillo, Texas, 1970, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Marlboro Heights Missionary Baptist Church, Killeen, Texas, 1982-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Carver High School, Waco, Texas, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Good Hope Western District Association, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Missionary Baptist General Convention of Texas, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Missionary Baptist General Convention of Texas, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Programs, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Blue Triangle YWCA, 1970-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sigma Gamma Rho Sorority, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Texas Association of Women's and Girl's Clubs, 1980, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Memorial Services, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Local Black History, 1984, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Black History, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)